transporting the foreign fighters to the border. These were networks of mercenaries, not ideologues, who were in the coordination business for profit. For example, they charged Saudi foreign fighters substantially more than Libyans, money that would have otherwise gone to al Qaeda. Perhaps the adversary would disrupt their own network if they knew they cheating would-be jihadists. In January, 2010, a devastating 7.0 earthquake struck Haiti, third deadliest earthquake of all time, left one million people, 10 percent of the population, homeless. One seemingly small aspect of the overall relief effort became increasingly important as the delivery of food and water started rolling. January and February are the dry months in Haiti, yet many of the camps had developed standing water. The only institution with detailed knowledge of Haiti's floodplains had been leveled in the earthquake, leadership inside. So the question is, which camps are at risk, how many people are in these camps, what's the timeline for flooding, and given very limited resources and infrastructure, how do we prioritize the relocation? The data was incredibly disparate. The U.S. Army had detailed knowledge for only a small section of the country. There was data online from a 2006 environmental risk conference, other geospatial data, none of it integrated. The human goal here was to identify camps for relocation based on priority need. The computer had to integrate a vast amount of geospacial information, social media data and relief organization information to answer this question. By implementing a superior process, what was otherwise a task for 40 people over three months became a simple job for three people in 40 hours, all victories for human-computer symbiosis. We're more than 50 years into Licklider's vision for the future, and the data suggests that we should be quite excited about tackling this century's hardest problems, man and machine in cooperation together. Thank you. (Applause) (Applause)
a los combatientes extranjeros hacia la frontera. Estas eran redes de mercenarios, no de ideólogos, que estaban en el negocio de la coordinación por las ganancias. Por ejemplo, a los combatientes sauditas les cobraban considerablemente más que a los libios; dinero que de otra manera habría sido para Al Qaeda. Tal vez el adversario interrumpiría su propia red si supiera que estaban engañando a aspirantes a yihadistas. En enero de 2010, un terremoto devastador de 7,0 grados sacudió Haití. El tercer terremoto más letal de la historia, dejó un millón de personas, el 10 % de la población, sin hogar. Un aspecto en apariencia pequeño de la ayuda humanitaria global se volvió cada vez más importante cuando comenzó la entrega de agua y alimentos. Enero y febrero son los meses secos en Haití, pero en muchos campamentos se habían formado aguas estancadas. La única institución con un conocimiento detallado de las llanuras aluviales de Haití se había derrumbado durante el terremoto, con sus líderes dentro. Así que la pregunta era: qué campamentos estaban en riesgo, cuánta gente había en esos campamentos, cuáles eran los plazos de las inundaciones y dados los muy escasos recursos e infraestructura, cómo priorizar el traslado. Los datos eran increíblemente dispares. El ejército de los EE.UU. tenía información detallada de solo una pequeña porción del país. Había datos en línea de una conferencia de riesgo ambiental de 2006, otros datos geoespaciales, nada de ello integrado. La meta humana era identificar los campamentos a trasladar en función de las necesidades prioritarias. La computadora debía integrar una gran cantidad de información geoespacial, datos de los medios sociales e información sobre la organización de ayuda humanitaria para responder a esta pregunta. Mediante la implementación de un proceso superior, lo que habría sido una tarea para 40 personas durante 3 meses, se volvió un trabajo simple para 3 personas en 40 horas, todas victorias de la simbiosis humano-computadora. Han pasado más de 50 años de la visión de Licklider para el futuro, y los datos sugieren que deberíamos sentirnos muy emocionados de poder atacar los problemas más difíciles del siglo, hombre y máquina cooperando juntos. Gracias. (Aplausos) (Aplausos)